Guide to the Dana Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Graduate student in mineralogy Sheffield Scientific School (1870-1872), and Heidelberg and Vienna (1872-1874); M.A. Yale 1874, Ph.D. 1876; tutor mathematics, physics, and chemistry at Yale 1874-1879, assistant professor of natural philosophy 1879-1890, professor of physics 1890-1917, professor emeritus since 1917; curator of mineralogy Peabody Museum 1874-1922; made important contributions to administration of Yale College through committee service, especially the Committee on the Course of Study (chairman 1906-1917) and Committee on Ways and Means (chairman 1911-1917); trustee Peabody Museum 1885-1929 (secretary 1895-1899, chairman 1899-1929); foremost American mineralogist of his time; made the first investigation of a rock and its constituents from the petrographic point of view (1872) and published the first important memoir in petrography to appear in the United States ("Trap Rocks of the Connecticut Valley," 1875); research activities (1872-1890) concerned with crystallographic and optical descriptions of minerals (47 papers); with his classmate George Bird Grinnell member of Captain Ludlow's expedition from Carroll, Montana Territory, to Yellowstone National Park, in summer of 1875; in January, 1875, became an editor of the American Journal of Science (founded in 1818 by his grandfather, Benjamin Silliman); served with his father and Benjamin Silliman, Jr., until February, 1885, with his father from March, 1885, to April, 1895, sole editor May, 1895, to 1926 when, owing to his serious illness, ownership of the magazine was transferred to Yale University; continued, however, until his death to assist in its publication; author: A Textbook of Mineralogy, with an Extended Treatise on Crystallography and Physical Mineralogy (1877; rewritten for edition of 1898); A Textbook of Elementary Mechanics, for the Use of Colleges and Schools (1881); sixth edition of the James D. Dana System of Mineralogy (1892); Minerals and How to Study Them (1895); co-author with Professor Chester R. Longwell, Walks and Rides in Central Connecticut and Massachusetts (1932); was a great lover of nature and a famous walker; had a summer home at Seal Harbor, Maine; Alumni Fund Agent for his Class since 1932; member Mineralogical Society of America (elected honorary president for life 1925); American Museum of Natural History and New York Mineralogical Society (elected honorary life member 1934); National Academy of Sciences (1884), Edinburgh Geological Society, Mineralogical Society of Great Britain, the Philosophical Society (Cambridge), and the Akademie der Wissenschaften (Vienna); corresponding member Vienna Reichsanstalt (elected 1874), Sociedad Mexicana de Historia Natural (elected 1874), Mineralogical Society of St. Petersburg (elected 1884); honorary member American Academy of Arts and Sciences, American Philosophical Society, Geological Society of America, and the Physical Society of America; foreign member of the Geological Society, London (corresponding member 1888).
Married October 2, 1883, in New Haven, Caroline, daughter of William Brooks Bristol (B.A. 1825) and Caroline (Bliss) Bristol, granddaughter of William Bristol (B.A. 1798), great-granddaughter of Moses Bliss (B.A. 1755) and of Simeon Bristol (B.A.1760), niece of Albert G. Bristol (B.A. 1827), and of Louis Bristol (B.A.1835), grandniece of George Bliss (B.A. 1784), and of William M. Bliss (B.A. 1790), and sister of Louis H. Bristol, '59, Eugene S. Bristol, '68 S., and John W. Bristol, '77. Children: Mary Bristol, the wife of Alexander C. Brown, '07; James Dwight, '11; and William Bristol, '18. Mrs. Dana died September 7, 1916.
Death due to arteriosclerosis. Buried at Seal Harbor, Maine. Survived by daughter, sons, seven grandchildren, one of whom is Alexander C. Brown, Jr., '35, a brother, Arnold G. Dana, '83, and a sister, Miss Maria Trumbull Dana, of New Haven.
Yale University Obituary Record, pp. 11-13.
Conditions Governing Access
The entire collection, excluding the additions, is available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 160 instead of the originals.
College students; Crustacea; Families; Geology; Mineralogy; Science; Voyages around the world; Voyages to the Pacific coast; Europe; Germany; Educators; Geologists; Agassiz, Louis, 1807-1873; Bache, A. D. (Alexander Dallas), 1806-1867; Bailey, Jacob Whitman, 1811-1857; Binney, Amos, 1803-1847; Dana, Edward Salisbury, 1849-1935; Dana, Harriet Dwight, 1792-1870; Dana, Henrietta Frances Silliman, 1823-1907; Dana, James Dwight, 1813-1895; Dana, James, 1780-1860; Dana, John White, 1817-1849; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882; Dwight, Timothy, 1828-1916; Gladstone, W. E. (William Ewart), 1809-1898; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888; Guyot, A. (Arnold), 1807-1884; Herrick, Edward Claudius, 1811-1862; Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1825-1895; Jones, Harriet Dwight Dana, 1820-1882; Möbius, Karl August, 1825-1908; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872; Nicklès, François Joseph Jʹerôme, 1821-1869; Norton, John Pitkin, 1822-1852; Park, Edwards Amasa, 1808-1900; Pierrepont, Edwards, 1817-1892; Quetelet, Adolphe, 1796-1874; Seward, William H. (William Henry), 1801-1872; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Sumner, William Graham, 1840-1910; Thompson, Joseph P. (Joseph Parrish), 1819-1879; Whitney, J. D. (Josiah Dwight), 1819-1896; Dana family; United States Exploring Expedition (1838-1842); Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University -- Faculty
- James Dwight Dana, 1805-1895; Series I; 5.5 linear feet (20 boxes)
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in three sections: Correspondence; Lectures notebooks, and miscellanea; and Writings and printed material.
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by individual.
  Lectures, notebooks, and miscellanea is arranged alphabetically by type.
  Writings and printed material is arranged by type and chronologically within each sub-section.
  Oversize items are arranged chronologically in box 20.
  Conditions Governing Access
  These materials are available on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 160 instead of the originals.
  - Correspondence
    - Abich, Herrman, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
    - Achiardi, Antonio d', 1875; 1881 (Box 1, Folder 1, Reel 1U)
    - Agassiz, Alexander, 1864-1892 (Box 1, Folder 2, Reel 1U)
    - Agassiz, Louis (*), 1847-1873, undated (Box 1, Folder 3, Reel 1U)
    - American Journal of Science, 1850, 1878-1879 (Box 1, Folder 4, Reel 1U)
    - Andrews, Ebenezer B., 1855-1856 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
    - Anstead, David Thomas, 1847-1848 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
    - Austin, B. W., 1885 (Box 1, Folder 5, Reel 1U)
    - Awards and Certificates (*), 1831-1895, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-8, Reel 1U)
      General note
      See also: box 20
    - Bache, Alexander Dallas, 1859; 1863 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
    - Bailey, Jacob Whitman, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
    - Bailer, Loring Woart, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
    - Baird, N., 1850 (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
    - Baird, William, undated (Box 1, Folder 9, Reel 1U)
    - Bakewell, Robert, 1839-1841 (Box 1, Folder 10, Reel 1U)
    - Ballard, Henry E., 1833 (Box 1, Folder 11, Reel 1U)
    - Bancroft, George, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
    - Barnard, James N., 1862 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
    - Barrande, [ ____ ], 1856; 1863 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
    - Barratt, Joseph, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 12, Reel 1U)
    - Barrois, Charles, 1888, undated (Box 1, Folder 13, Reel 1U)
    - Barrtlett, Charles, undated (Box 1, Folder 13, Reel 1U)
    - Bawerbank, J., 1848 (Box 1, Folder 13, Reel 1U)
    - Bechi, Emile, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 13, Reel 1U)
    - Bell, Thomas, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 13, Reel 1U)
    - Benton, Thomas Hart, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 14, Reel 1U)
    - Berzelius, Jons-Jacob, 1836; 1844 (Box 1, Folder 15, Reel 1U)
    - Billings, E., 1871 (Box 1, Folder 16, Reel 1U)
    - Binney, Amos, 1846 (Box 1, Folder 16, Reel 1U)
    - Blonford, William Thomas, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 16, Reel 1U)
    - Boeckh, [ ____ ], 1856 (Box 1, Folder 16, Reel 1U)
    - Bond, G. P., 1856 (Box 1, Folder 16, Reel 1U)
    - Bond, William Cranch, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 16, Reel 1U)
    - Bonney, Thomas George, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 16, Reel 1U)
    - Boston Society of Natural History, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 17, Reel 1U)
    - Brogniart, Charles, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 18, Reel 1U)
    - Bronn, Heinrich George, 1885; 1860 (Box 1, Folder 18, Reel 1U)
    - Brullé, Gaspard Auguste, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 18, Reel 1U)
    - Buck, (Mrs.) William I., 1837 (Box 1, Folder 19, Reel 1U)
    - Campbell, H. D., 1893 (Box 1, Folder 20, Reel 1U)
    - Candee, John D., 1875 (Box 1, Folder 20, Reel 1U)
    - Capellini, J., 1887 (Box 1, Folder 20, Reel 1U)
    - Carruth, James Harrison, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 20, Reel 1U)
    - Carus, J. Victor, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 20, Reel 1U)
    - Caswell, A., 1856 (Box 1, Folder 21, Reel 1U)
    - Chace, George Ides, 1856; 1875 (Box 1, Folder 21, Reel 1U)
    - Chapin, James H., 1880 (Box 1, Folder 21, Reel 1U)
    - Clarke, William B., 1857 (Box 1, Folder 21, Reel 1U)
    - Clingman, T. L., 1856 (Box 1, Folder 21, Reel 1U)
    - Clippings-[Silliman; Dana], undated (Box 1, Folder 22, Reel 1U)
    - Clochi, Igino, 1871-1889 (Box 1, Folder 23, Reel 1U)
    - Croll, James, 1876 (Box 1, Folder 23, Reel 1U)
    - Conant, C. B., 1835 (Box 1, Folder 23, Reel 1U)
    - Dall, W., 1888 (Box 1, Folder 24, Reel 1U)
    - Dalyell, John Graham, 1846-1848 (Box 1, Folder 24, Reel 1U)
    - Damour, A., 1868 (Box 1, Folder 24, Reel 1U)
    - Dana Charles Anderson, 1871-1891 (Box 1, Folder 25, Reel 1U)
    - Dana, Cornelia Elizabeth, 1840-1843 (Box 1, Folder 26, Reel 1U)
    - Dana, Edward S. (*), 1872-1892, undated (Box 1, Folder 27-28, Reel 1U)
    - Dana, George Strong, (*), 1834-1839 (Box 1, Folder 29, Reel 1U)
    - Dana, Harriet Dwight, (*), 1833-1852 (Box 1, Folder 30, Reel 1U)
    - Dana, Henrietta Silliman, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 31, Reel 1U)
    - Dana, James, (*), 1805-1844 (Box 1, Folder 32-33, Reel 1U)
    - Dana, James Dwight, (*), 1894 (Box 1, Folder 32-33, Reel 1U)
      - Wedding anniversary, 50th, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 34, Reel 1U)
      - Miscellaneous, 1833-1895, undated (Box 1, Folder 35, Reel 1U)
      - Sketches, undated (Box 1, Folder 36, Reel 1U)
    - Dana, James Freeman, undated (Box 1, Folder 37, Reel 1U)
    - Dana, John White, 1833-1840 (Box 1, Folder 38, Reel 1U)
    - Dana, Richard Henry, Jr.
      - Correspondence, 1856-1876 (Box 1, Folder 39, Reel 1U)
      - Journal: photostat, 1815-1833 (Box 1, Folder 40, Reel 1U)
    - Dana, Sam L. (?), undated (Box 1, Folder 41, Reel 1U)
    - Dana, William Buck, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 42, Reel 1U)
    - Darwin, Charles, (*), 1849-1853; 1856-1863; 1896, undated (Box 2, Folder 43-44, Reel 2U)
    - Darwin, Francis, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 45, Reel 2U)
    - Daubrée, Auguste, 1864-1895 (Box 2, Folder 46, Reel 2U)
    - Davis, Charles Henry, 1852-1859 (Box 2, Folder 47, Reel 2U)
    - Davis, E. C., 1875 (Box 2, Folder 47, Reel 2U)
    - Davison, Charles, 1888-1894 (Box 2, Folder 47, Reel 2U)
    - Dawkins, William Boyd, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 47, Reel 2U)
    - Dawson, George M., 1893 (Box 2, Folder 47, Reel 2U)
    - Dawson, John William, 1856, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 47, Reel 2U)
    - Deane, James, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 48, Reel 2U)
    - DeCandolle, Alphonse, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 48, Reel 2U)
    - Dellay, James E., 1846 (Box 2, Folder 48, Reel 2U)
    - Delafield, Joseph, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 48, Reel 2U)
    - Delesse, Achille Ernest and Oscar Joseph, 1869-1893 (Box 2, Folder 48, Reel 2U)
    - Delgado, Joaquina, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 48, Reel 2U)
    - Derby, Orville A., 1881 (Box 2, Folder 49, Reel 2U)
    - Descloizeaux, Alfred Louis, 1863-1869 (Box 2, Folder 49, Reel 2U)
    - Dewalque, G., 1881 (Box 2, Folder 49, Reel 2U)
    - Dewey, Chester, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 49, Reel 2U)
    - Diller, J. S., 1876-1877 (Box 2, Folder 49, Reel 2U)
    - Dohrn, Anton, 1872, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 50, Reel 2U)
    - Domeyko, Ignace, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 50, Reel 2U)
    - Draper, Henry, 1880 (Box 2, Folder 50, Reel 2U)
    - Draper, John W., 1876 (Box 2, Folder 50, Reel 2U)
    - Drayton, John, 1841-1853 (Box 2, Folder 50, Reel 2U)
    - Dulton, Clarence Edward, 1841-1853 (Box 2, Folder 50, Reel 2U)
    - Dwight, Timothy, 1891-1894 (Box 2, Folder 51, Reel 2U)
    - Ehrenberg, Christian Gottfied, 851 (Box 2, Folder 52, Reel 2U)
    - Ellis, George A., 1875 (Box 2, Folder 52, Reel 2U)
    - Emerson, Benjamin Kendall, undated (Box 2, Folder 52, Reel 2U)
    - Encke, Johann Franz, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 52, Reel 2U)
    - Erdmann, Edvard, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 52, Reel 2U)
    - Erenbeck, [ ____ ], 1857 (Box 2, Folder 52, Reel 2U)
    - Etheridge, Robert, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 52, Reel 2U)
    - Forbes, David, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 53, Reel 2U)
    - Forbes, James David, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 53, Reel 2U)
    - Forehhammer, Johann George, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 53, Reel 2U)
    - Forel, F. A., 1892 (Box 2, Folder 53, Reel 2U)
    - Fouqué, Ferdinand Andre, 1887, undated (Box 2, Folder 53, Reel 2U)
    - Frenzel, August, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 53, Reel 2U)
    - Fuchs, Th., 1885 (Box 2, Folder 53, Reel 2U)
    - Gabb, William More, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 54, Reel 2U)
    - Gramble, William, 1849 (Box 2, Folder 54, Reel 2U)
    - Gardiner, [ ____ ], 1873 (Box 2, Folder 54, Reel 2U)
    - Gegenbauer, [ ____ ], 1869 (Box 2, Folder 54, Reel 2U)
    - Geikie, Archibald, 1880-1889 (Box 2, Folder 54, Reel 2U)
    - Geikie, James, 1879-1884 (Box 2, Folder 54, Reel 2U)
    - Geinitz, Harms Bruno, 1855-1889 (Box 2, Folder 55, Reel 2U)
    - Genth, Frederick Augustus, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 55, Reel 2U)
    - Giebel, C., 1852 (Box 2, Folder 55, Reel 2U)
    - Gillis, James Melville, 1836-1836 (Box 2, Folder 55, Reel 2U)
    - Gilman, Daniel C., 1853 (Box 2, Folder 55, Reel 2U)
    - Gladstone, William E., 1885-1886, undated (Box 2, Folder 56, Reel 2U)
    - Goodall, George Lincoln, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 57, Reel 2U)
    - Gould, Augustus Addison, 1853-1857 (Box 2, Folder 57, Reel 2U)
    - Gould, Benjamin Apthorp, 1856-1884 (Box 2, Folder 57, Reel 2U)
    - Gould, John, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 57, Reel 2U)
    - Gray, Asa (*), 1833-1886 (Box 2, Folder 59, Reel 2U)
    - Groth, Paul Heinrich, 1876 (?) (Box 2, Folder 60, Reel 2U)
    - Guyot, Arnold, (*), 1856-1881 (Box 2, Folder 61, Reel 2U)
    - Haidinger, Wilhelm Karl, 1854-1859 (Box 2, Folder 62, Reel 2U)
    - Haldeman, Samuel Steman, 1846, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 62, Reel 2U)
    - Hall, James, 1846-1855 (Box 2, Folder 62, Reel 2U)
    - Hamilton, William J., 1848-1849 (Box 2, Folder 62, Reel 2U)
    - Harkness, William, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 62, Reel 2U)
    - Harris, Thaddeus William, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 62, Reel 2U)
    - Harvard Quinquennial Catalogue, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 63, Reel 2U)
    - Haughton, Samuel, 1867, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 64, Reel 2U)
    - Hayes, Augustus Allen, 1854, undated (Box 2, Folder 64, Reel 2U)
    - Hayes, Isaac Israel, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 64, Reel 2U)
    - Heddle, M. F., 1878 (Box 2, Folder 64, Reel 2U)
    - Hemery, Franz von, 1885 (Box 2, Folder 64, Reel 2U)
    - Hennessy, Henry, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 64, Reel 2U)
    - Henry, Joseph, 1855-1874 (Box 2, Folder 65, Reel 2U)
    - Herrick, Edward Claudius, 1833 (Box 2, Folder 65, Reel 2U)
    - Hessenberg, Friedrich, 1868 (Box 2, Folder 65, Reel 2U)
    - Hewitt, Abram Stevens, 1872 (Box 2, Folder 65, Reel 2U)
    - Higgins, William, undated (Box 2, Folder 65, Reel 2U)
    - Hildreth, Samuel Prescott, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 65, Reel 2U)
    - Hilgard, Eugene W., 1887 (Box 2, Folder 65, Reel 2U)
    - Hill, Robett T., 1894 (Box 2, Folder 65, Reel 2U)
    - Hills, R. C., 1892 (Box 2, Folder 65, Reel 2U)
    - Hinde, George, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 65, Reel 2U)
    - Hitchcock, C. H., 1883 (Box 2, Folder 66, Reel 2U)
    - Hitchcock, Edward, 1845-1862 (Box 2, Folder 66, Reel 2U)
    - Hooker, Sir Joseph, 1877-1878 (Box 2, Folder 66, Reel 2U)
    - Hubbard, Faith Silliman, 1843 (Box 2, Folder 67, Reel 2U)
    - Hugard, undated (Box 2, Folder 68, Reel 2U)
    - Hull, Edward, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 68, Reel 2U)
    - Humboldt, A. V., 1856 (Box 2, Folder 68, Reel 2U)
    - Humphreys, A. A., 1881 (Box 2, Folder 68, Reel 2U)
    - Hunt, Edward Bissell, 1856-1858 (Box 2, Folder 69, Reel 2U)
    - Hunt, T. Sterry, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 69, Reel 2U)
    - Huxley, Thomas Henry, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 69, Reel 2U)
    - Hyatt, Alpheus, 1870, undated (Box 2, Folder 69, Reel 2U)
    - Jackson, C. T., 1848 (Box 2, Folder 70, Reel 2U)
    - Jager, Georg Friedrich, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 70, Reel 2U)
    - Jones, George, 1852-1857 (Box 2, Folder 70, Reel 2U)
    - Jones, Harriet D. Dana, 1833-1849 (Box 2, Folder 71, Reel 2U)
    - Joy, Charles A., 1856 (Box 2, Folder 72, Reel 2U)
    - Judd, John W., 1882-1891 (Box 2, Folder 72, Reel 2U)
    - Jukes, J. Beete, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 72, Reel 2U)
    - Kane, John Kintzing, 1858 (Box 2, Folder 73, Reel 2U)
    - Kayser, E., 1891 (Box 2, Folder 73, Reel 2U)
    - Kenngott, Adolf, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 73, Reel 2U)
    - Keyserling, Alexander (Box 2, Folder 73, Reel 2U)
    - Friedrich Henry, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 73, Reel 2U)
    - Kinahan, G., 1871 (Box 2, Folder 73, Reel 2U)
    - King, H., 1848 (Box 2, Folder 73, Reel 2U)
    - King, William, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 73, Reel 2U)
    - Kirkwood, Daniel, 1850-1851 (Box 2, Folder 74, Reel 2U)
    - Kokscharow, Nikolai Ivanovich, 1853-1856, undated (Box 2, Folder 74, Reel 2U)
    - Konineck, L., 1852-1855 (Box 2, Folder 74, Reel 2U)
    - Kopp, Hermann, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 74, Reel 2U)
    - Koto, B., 1887 (Box 2, Folder 74, Reel 2U)
    - Kraup, [ ____ ], 1854 (Box 2, Folder 74, Reel 2U)
    - Lane, John H., 1852 (Box 2, Folder 75, Reel 2U)
    - Lapparent, Albert de, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 75, Reel 2U)
    - Lapworth, Charles, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 75, Reel 2U)
    - Ladrey, [ ____ ], 1854-1858 (Box 2, Folder 75, Reel 2U)
    - Lawrence, J., 1846 (Box 2, Folder 75, Reel 2U)
    - Lea, Isaac, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 75, Reel 2U)
    - Lehmann, Richard, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 75, Reel 2U)
    - Leidy, Joseph, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 75, Reel 2U)
    - Leonhard, Gustav, 1845-1852 (Box 2, Folder 75, Reel 2U)
    - Lesley, John Peter, 1889-1892 (Box 2, Folder 76, Reel 2U)
    - Lesquereux, Leo, 1886-1889 (Box 2, Folder 76, Reel 2U)
    - Lettsom, W. G., 1857-1874 (Box 2, Folder 76, Reel 2U)
    - Leverett, Frank, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 76, Reel 2U)
    - Levy, Armand, 1840 (Box 2, Folder 76, Reel 2U)
    - Lewis, Tayler, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 76, Reel 2U)
    - Lieber, Francis, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 76, Reel 2U)
    - Liebig, Justus, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 76, Reel 2U)
    - Lockyer, Joseph Norman, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 77, Reel 2U)
    - Logan, William E., 1872 (Box 2, Folder 77, Reel 2U)
    - Lonsdale, William, 1846-1849 (Box 2, Folder 77, Reel 2U)
    - Loven, Sven, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 77, Reel 2U)
    - Lovering, Joseph, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 77, Reel 2U)
    - Lowell, J. A., 1853 (Box 2, Folder 77, Reel 2U)
    - Lubbock, J., 1854, undated (Box 2, Folder 77, Reel 2U)
    - Lundbohm, Hjalmar, 1889 (Box 2, Folder 77, Reel 2U)
    - Lyell, Charles, 1852, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 77, Reel 2U)
    - McCoy, Frederick, 1844-1847 (Box 2, Folder 78, Reel 2U)
    - McColloh, R. S., 1856 (Box 2, Folder 78, Reel 2U)
    - Macgowan, [ ____ ], 1854 (Box 2, Folder 78, Reel 2U)
    - Mackie, James G., 1858 (Box 2, Folder 78, Reel 2U)
    - Mallet, Robert, 1873-1875 (Box 2, Folder 78, Reel 2U)
    - Mann, Johannes G. de, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 78, Reel 2U)
    - Mantell, Gideon Algernon, 1846 (Box 2, Folder 78, Reel 2U)
    - Margeric, Emmanuelde, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 78, Reel 2U)
    - Marignac, Jean Charles Galissard de, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 78, Reel 2U)
    - Marsh, George Perkins, 1846-1848 (Box 2, Folder 78, Reel 2U)
    - Maskelyne, Nevil S., 1868, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 79, Reel 2U)
    - Mayer, Alfred Marshall, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 79, Reel 2U)
    - Meek, Fielding Bradford, 1860-1873 (Box 2, Folder 79, Reel 2U)
    - Meneghini, Joseph (Guiseppe), 1852-1881 (Box 2, Folder 79, Reel 2U)
    - Merriam, G. & C., 1864 (Box 2, Folder 79, Reel 2U)
    - Merris Pack Bros., 13 April 1895 (Box 2, Folder 80, Reel 2U)
    - Metcalf, L. S., 1887 (Box 2, Folder 81, Reel 2U)
    - Michelin, Hardovin, 1846 (Box 2, Folder 81, Reel 2U)
    - Miller, William H., 1868 (Box 2, Folder 81, Reel 2U)
    - Milne-Edwards, Alphonse, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 81, Reel 2U)
    - Milne-Edwards, Henri, 1843-1847 (Box 2, Folder 81, Reel 2U)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 82, Reel 2U)
    - Mitchell, Donald G., 1884, undated (Box 2, Folder 83, Reel 2U)
    - Mitchell, Maria, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 83, Reel 2U)
    - Mobius, Karl, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 83, Reel 2U)
    - Moigno, Abbé Francois N., 1846 (Box 2, Folder 83, Reel 2U)
    - Morris, John, 1843-1845 (Box 2, Folder 83, Reel 2U)
    - Morse, Edward Sylvester, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 83, Reel 2U)
    - Morse, Samuel Finley Breeze, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 84, Reel 2U)
    - Morton, Samuel George, 1850, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 84, Reel 2U)
    - Mudge, Benjamin Franklin, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 84, Reel 2U)
    - Muller, Johann, 1854 (Box 2, Folder 84, Reel 2U)
    - Murchison, Roderick Impey, 1856-1863, undated (Box 2, Folder 84, Reel 2U)
    - Murray, Alexander, 1882-1883 (Box 2, Folder 84, Reel 2U)
    - Nelson, Richard J., 1872 (Box 3, Folder 85, Reel 3U)
    - Nickles, Jerome, 1852-1867, undated (Box 3, Folder 86, Reel 3U)
    - Norpé, H. de, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 87, Reel 3U)
    - Nordenskiold, Nils Adolf Erik, 1865-1868 (Box 3, Folder 87, Reel 3U)
    - Norton, John Pitkin, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 87, Reel 3U)
    - Norton, John Treadwell, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 87, Reel 3U)
    - Orbigny, Alcide Dessalines de, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 88, Reel 3U)
    - Ord, George, 1849 (Box 3, Folder 88, Reel 3U)
    - Owen, David D., 1854 (Box 3, Folder 88, Reel 3U)
    - Owen, George, 1882 (Box 3, Folder 88, Reel 3U)
    - Owen, Richard, 1864 (Box 3, Folder 88, Reel 3U)
    - Owen, Sir Richard, 1863 (Box 3, Folder 88, Reel 3U)
    - Paine, Robert Treat, 1865 (Box 3, Folder 89, Reel 3U)
    - Pallesina, [ ____ ], 1886 (Box 3, Folder 89, Reel 3U)
    - Palmer, J. C., 1840-1842 (Box 3, Folder 90, Reel 3U)
    - Park, Edwardo Amasa, 1855-1857 (Box 3, Folder 91, Reel 3U)
    - Paykull, C. W., 1867 (Box 3, Folder 91, Reel 3U)
    - Peirce, Benjamin, 1851-1878 (Box 3, Folder 91, Reel 3U)
    - Peirce, Charles Santiago Sanders, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 91, Reel 3U)
    - Perry, Alexis, 1853-1861 (Box 3, Folder 91, Reel 3U)
    - Petermann, August, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 92, Reel 3U)
    - Phillips, John Arthur, 1867 (Box 3, Folder 92, Reel 3U)
    - Phillips, Wendell, 1857 (Box 3, Folder 92, Reel 3U)
    - Philosophical Magazine, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 92, Reel 3U)
    - Pickering, Charles, 1850-1872 (Box 3, Folder 92, Reel 3U)
    - Piddington, (William?), 1855 (Box 3, Folder 93, Reel 3U)
    - Pierrepont, Edwards, 1877-1878 (Box 3, Folder 93, Reel 3U)
    - Pierson, S., 1875-1877 (Box 3, Folder 93, Reel 3U)
    - Poey, Felipe, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 93, Reel 3U)
    - Poggendorf, Johann C., 1853 (Box 3, Folder 93, Reel 3U)
    - Portales, Louis F., 1871-1878 (Box 3, Folder 94, Reel 3U)
    - Prestwich, Joseph, 1878-1886 (Box 3, Folder 94, Reel 3U)
    - Prevost, Constant, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 94, Reel 3U)
    - Prince, Dr., 1879 (Box 3, Folder 94, Reel 3U)
    - Quatrefages de Bréau, Armand de, 1846 (Box 3, Folder 94, Reel 3U)
    - Quetelet, Lambert-Adolphe Jacques, 1851-1866 (Box 3, Folder 94, Reel 3U)
    - Rammelsberg, Karl Friedrich, 1851 (Box 3, Folder 95, Reel 3U)
    - Ramsay, Andrew Crombie, 1858-1863 (Box 3, Folder 95, Reel 3U)
    - Reade, T. Millard, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 95, Reel 3U)
    - Reichenbach, Karl, undated (Box 3, Folder 95, Reel 3U)
    - Renand, Charles, 1870 (Box 3, Folder 95, Reel 3U)
    - Renevier, Eugène, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 96, Reel 3U)